Welcome my name is claudio I'm a program managing the
...team and today I'm here to present one of
the programming model that are available for a newvery
...technology that is...service public?
So, today we are going to talk about
these technology it was announced...week
so you should probably you probably had the chance to read about it and,
you may also have seen these slide this is basically what
service public is a...I knew framework I
...runtime environment...design to allow
I scalable michael service base application two-run
...and also on prime as you can see that are a lot of
different features that comes b with the application with the framework itself
there is a high-density there is high availability the ability to scale application
or are feature that artability in the platform in addition to that there are also
different programming models are different way to write application four-d
...platform and today we're going to discuss one of them that
these core what we codyreliable actors?
Let me move very quickly
are very brief introduction if you're not already familiar with the actor
...is not a new idea it was invented about forty years
ago by car you would he basically designed is a thought about these new
model...application that was base on independent
units where both state?
And, code could be encapsulated together and then
...communication was done through some sort of messaging
system so that model these...became a very interesting
in the last few years because of the new requirement
...highly scalable application are there are nowyou know, we'd cloud solution that are
you can potentially ev access to under the of course so now the challenges
...to be the application that can really leverage that sort of
...infrastructure and act torso seems to be a one-way
that you can design application that really allows you to leverage that very
powerful infrastructure by keeping somehow the idea the design of the application
a relatively simple in addition to these encapsulation of coding state
a synchronous communication a...social provide the ability to
...single...and activity supposed to be single...so
...complexity of designing and daily with multi-threaded type of
...that you can avoid we dactor...there are
...implementations are both in the sort of not dot net toward
bottles on the other...runtime environments probably one of the most famous one
...the one used by arlen.
So, less dearly the bit into
why we need an actor model so in the old days the application word be
used in the multiple layers...typical trickier striper level otherwise
...web from ten there was a middle tier or...business logical
...application...typo layer and then there was
an axis data base and storage layer rd challenge we did that type of
model there was a really dealing with the discover ability
of the application so typically in all the application may be becomes very
...more customers want to connect to it and then what happens is that the first
lehrer layer probably is...a web from
...needs to be replicated to provide to be able to...more traffic
then you know, the next level would be probably the application server layer and then
...database layer...each of these steps as a
developer it was always challenging to try to find the right
tradeoff between adding more components like
...a q system in order to piper and...and q requested and,
maybe...systems in order to provide...low latency or
reduced latency for end-users we the internet skate or cloud not
if type of applications what happens is that the idea is to be
the application a very different weight and the way is to create
...something that is...finer granularity over
...components...application and try to build basically what now is
...as a michael service architecture so basically split all the functionality your application...
more depose more manageable components that can potential be replicated
base...the workload and the idea is to provide elasticity the
...based...in such a way that the system somehow is
able to react automatically base on the demand so on the left on the
right you see that there is the sort of a new idea where you have
typically a from tandy can be a load balance or something that provides the public can
point and then there are machines, you know, can be, you know,a cluster what we
can call a cluster any side that cluster there are multiple independent components
...interact with each other in order to provide the functionality
...required so in this...new model?
We have the service fabric that is the underneath infrastructure so that's sort of
cluster management
...that we need and then we have the fabric reliable
actors that the programming model that he we can add on top
of the runtime in order to build our applications and then beam base on
...type of design we get some of the feature that comes with the actor
...and typically the resource isolation as a were saying before the ability
...state encoder together the are synchronous
communication okay that is very important in order to achieve scaleability and also
...single...so when I write to the code for my actor I don't really need to
...into complex...type of
code that clearly is very difficult to write and get it right so in addition
of being based on the service
...fabric what do we get is some additional benefit and one of them is
...transparency location
transparency basically means that in order for me to be able to interact
to send quote-unquote send a message to an actor I really don't need to know where that
...is going to be located within my cluster I
...very easy way to porting put
...to that doctor in such a way that I don't really need to manage
format developer from my application point of view the actual location
...being able tokeep track aware my actor are going to be allocated.
In addition to that we basically built the synchronous communication
model is also based on our request response type of...so...very
easy-to-use I send...to an actor the request is going to be a synchronous so
...not going to be blocking from my side but at the same time I have this pattern over
...respond so I know that I will...back so the
logically my called doesn't need to really have to deal with complex a
synchronous are being able to track for instance what type of...in order to be
...for instance to process...mesh search coming back from another actor.
And, then the thing that is
...windows fabric is the automatic fail over so
...an actor the actor my failed for some sort of reason can be the code itself that is
fairly already maybe that is the node where that specific actor was running that
...paley and what are the windows fabric a
infrastructure does is ultimately reallocate the actor on another
node or potentially restart the know the actively...in such a way that from
a developer point of view I don't have to deal with the sort-of failed over type of scenarios?
In addition to that...other important
feature is I have the ability to upgrade.
The actors inwhat we call...downtime type of fashion so I
ever running service the service is compose of multiple actors the
actors can be a upgraded over time without
any interruption the worst-case scenario is my the users on the other side
will see a very is more of...are in there sort of interaction with the
...but nothing is sort of lost I don't need to start
a machine I do need to go through complex deployment process?
So, all of these are...that comes with the actor
...being built on top of the service fabric infrastructure so
let's see what more in detail what does it mean to build really an actor
...solution so in order to build
...liable actors of application the first thing that
they need to do and you will see that the process the time following is something that these really should be very from
...nothing really new is very similar to the same process that you go through by building
a standard...oriented base that type of
application so the first thing that I do is I define
the actor interfaces so basically the actor interface define what do we can
...quote-unquote the messages so the type of messages that
the actor is able to process and will allow a third-party that can be
...application already can be another actor to interact with that specific
...the time about to define...step I just need to implement
dee interface...a class that derided for something
that these called an actor so basically you take like you would do in any sort of
object-oriented type of application you take a class you derive from it you
implementer interface that basically...business logic the
code that define my actor in addition to that we'll see I have a slide
about that later that we also cr we actually go into
...package these actor together in such a way that they become quote-unquote
...service ...a
...entity that can really run inside the service public infrastructure then that
thirst type is I need to registered the actor and basically registering the
actor means that I led to the service probability infrastructure
node that there is a new quote-unquote type a new entity that
can be instantiated so any other application...service
or program that is running we...service tropic infrastructure
will be able to use these new entity and then the last
step is in order to communicate with actors so if I want to
evoke one specific message I want to send a measure to an actor the way that I do it is
with something that we call an actor proxy inductor proxy is
a class of the entity that provide that sort of location
transparency that is an additional benefit of the actor
...running on top of the service public so I really don't need to a I have complex
business logic in myapplication in order to end-all where, you know, and,
to manage where...are located I can use the actor proxy
...provide me all the ability of in all
...fail over management so let's assume that
I'm working with an actor that specific actor is
...one node in the cluster that node my...so the activities
...allocated to another node by using the actor proxy I can just core
reactor again I don't really need to figure out or no even know that
...doctor
...actually moved to a different node so the actor proxy provide a very easy way to interact
with actors actor proxy is use both my client application and
we will see different types of client applications but also between
...actor to actor type of communication?
So, before we go into more some real code that we can show I want to spend, you
know, one-minute to explain the our applications and services are really package
and deployed on theservice public infrastructure in this case I have a
...I have a set of actors the...the fine I can,
you know, I have a lot of flexibility I can decide that, you know,
one...is one service
...the service superstructure or I can package multiple...together
...one single service so I have basically one entity that di I take all
the code I package together and potentially I might have also some
configuration some doctor that I need to package along with my code I
package in something that the school of service package and then I have
an application package that is basically may
logic unit of deployment for service public for service fabric and what
the application package gives me is basically three different things number one is
the you need to where I can manage the lifetime of my application so
...application is deployed...application is activated...the
...okay the second thing is versioning and application define I
can have multiple version of an application and then is the
logical unit in which I want to version one specific set potentially
of services so if I have a set of services that define my maybe my
end-to-end solution for a customer that becomes an application that I can rev
...have I can deploy multiple version of that by taking care...
a managing all the different components as one singlelogical unit and
then...the same time...provides isolation
...the application itself and all...services inside application
can run...specific forty-some security requirements that
...application-level however really...very...type of control over
...package my different services that by the way I can be
...a across multiple applications or
...configured that specific application in order to run in the service
fabric so once I have my service package I package them, you know,
I can have multiple...case, you know,
I have to services another point I have one single unita that can deployed in the service
public infrastructure so let's goal and, show some code
sothe first thing that they want to show is rd a developer experience
looks like a so first of all for service fabric d typical
developer environment is compose by clearly visual studio with service poverty
...a new project system that allows you to
...to different type of service fabric
our services and applications and then is also...on the
loca cluster so only your local machine in this case might laptop I have
...runtime environment that I can deploy that can be deployed on
...social multiple machines everything is running on
the same on the same box is sort of similar to the as
...emulator sort of thing but...very close to
...the runtime environment is going-to be so...application...ranch
...your local cluster is going to run a aziz on a production environment on
...so here I have visual studio I installed the service fabric
...so let me first of all show the canonical
low war-type of application so once you go into
the visual studio environment you have clearly the ability so let me
show very quickly the ability to create a new project so under clouded
...a new category service fabric and you see that...you can create
a different type of services so the visual studio tools for service
fabric we provide you are set of templates that you can is in order to quote-unquote
...to the type of service that you want
to build in our case you see that I will focus on the service public...service-type
all projects so here just to save a little bit of time ip recreatedthe typical
...war-type of scenario so let me sure...our solution will look like so I
...first of...we discuss the step number one is to define the?
Interfaces so when they create a solution I have one project in my solution that
defined interfaces here you see that I have in this case
...interfaces very simple...have one single
method that is say award and the only thing that I need to do is
to derived interface from I actor in such a way that the disservice
property professionals...to end-all and...to manage these interfaces in this
specific...when you create a new project these the...creates
...simple interface already so what you can do is just
to customize and...that these already provided by you by
...so after I have the interface to in this case I...is a said,
you know, I create the only one method that
...say yellow I go to the next part of the application that
is in this case the award and hilo ward is what we
...just before in...before is the service so the it is
...logically unit where the actor is going to be
packaged inside in such a way that the becomes an entity that
camron inside the service...infrastructure so the thing that they need to do in this
...project is let me actually take dl award?
Actor so you see that here I have my actor I
have yellow actor either...for one specificclass that these the
actor class and then the thing that I'm doing is to create and
...the award the
interface so as you can see here visual studio raid p...some
border...type of code that is the typical code that you need to
ave we d an actor and let me walk through very quickly some of the
...so we have a method for into that is called on activate these
method these is called when the actor is going to be activated by the runtime
environment so here for instance you can write some initialization code that you
may need to every your application typically you might have a configure file where you
re some parameters audio connect to some sort of external
...can system in order to collect some data that needs to be available while the
...is oper running there is another method that is...
on the activate so when the actor is going to be the activated I will
spend few words later to explain what that means and then as you can
see here I have basically the implementation of the say hello
so say aloe in this case basically take one parameter and what I'm doing is basically
just sending back to we what whatever is calling me in
this specific case basically one stream we degree thing that I got with you know, a
string so is very simple very simple implementation
so one more note you see that here I have also the is classes service
event source class this is something that comes again with the template that is generated
by visual studio and basically give you the ability to create a
...events they can be used for logging in
tracing type of scenarios so along with
being able to debug my application I also have the ability to have a very a
reach...eighty w set of events that I can fully
...such a way that when my application is deploys
...I have the ability to figure out what is going on with my system
so I have these application and then let me show you the thing that doesn't come by
defaultyet we're going to add that by the time by next week for
...so here is declined application and let me
...actually sorry before we go that...showed the
third step I forgot to mention that the first step if you remember ...the previous slide
...about a registering the actor and then here it is
our these done so I have basically?
One class that these provide by the runtime and then during that class I do
the actor registration other point
...with these line I basically making my actor
...available to or
services and application running on the service public infrastructure so by
default the visual studio solution create one for you but if
you implement multiple actors in the same project you will have basically to
add additional lines like these in order to register...actors that you might
have in your application so we went through the interfaces we show the
actor implementation with interface we show the
act or registration and then the last step the fourth step was basically
the actor proxy so in this case...I added...client application just to the
...that actually the actor is working and then here you see that is the way
that I am using the actor proxy so the actor...
the ability to connect to bind to an actor and this is basically our...do it I have an
actor proxies I say create and create the doesn't always mean
create, create means create if the actor is not active or ict means
...bind if the actor is already running I specify the type of interface
so what type of communication I want to...this case I want to communicate with the
award actor and then basically I define an actor idea specify an
act already I will spend a little bit of time later to explain
what that means and then I have the application name
...basically define the application as I showed before in
the previous slide that is the entity that encapsulated that the package
different services in my application in this case I have one application that is
composer one single service so I want to show you
one quick thing so let's go to dl award say a
...I can for instance set...break point.
A here.
I go to my...application you cd
...award application is the service fabric application
eighties the application that manages the entire life-cycle of my applications
so the build process deployment process debugging so on so by
default eighties di the startup project so the only thing that I need to do in this
case if you see here I have the ability to for instance
...remover...package my application and do additional operations
on my application so the theater need to do unlike any other
...to the application I just need to...a five and what
...this is going to do is basically to package my applications so compile
the code packaged applications so basically...that sort of application package that I
showed you before and then basically take the application deployed the application the
...cluster and...as you can see on the output windowed
...visual...telling me what is happening so are the process
is progressing over time with my package being deployed on the loca
...and then here you see that I have the diagnostic events that basically show me
the audited w events that I used in my
application so I can very easily see what is happening on my
applications so now I have dee service fabric applications deployed
my activities raided to be used so let me switch very quickly to the lowered
client so I have a very simple console client so here and,
...clients so now what I'm doing I'm luncheon declined application?
And, as you can see like any other visual to
the application the actor proxy cody actor cody say a little
...and the in the sale...break...so
...have the ability to debug my applications like any other visual studio
application so in...as you can see high basically...the client
...I have, you know, that is the idea of the actor that I
was calling here that it is and then basically actually I didn't
send any message but this is basically the...apply that I got back from the.
...actor and then as you can see here I have an old di for each
...this is deed...event the
...register in my are sale awarded method when
it was invoked so here you can see that I have the ability...very
easily a...what is happening in production we'd a set of
...prevents ok so this is a very simple example I want to spend
one week one more thing so actually let's kill this I want to load
the one different solution so,
let's ...solution is exactly the same
solution so one thing that I want to show you is,
you know, I...I said a lot about
actors but there is one specific thing in the name of
our new technology that is called reliable actors I want to show you a little bit about
what that means so here I have another project is a very simple actor
he's an actor that as let me should be the interface here I basically
have the ability to get them set...a counter so I have an actor that basically save a local
...so I can read the counter or I can set...the counter to a new value
okay so it's very simple I have a client application I have
interfaces like before so let me do a very simple
here so instead of going to the debug process of this point I don't really need to go
...debug process I just want to...solution so I go to
deploy so now what happens is that my applications going to be deployed suomi
...cluster okay so let me go to the client application.
so here I have my counter application and,
if I start my counter application you see that these is very simple is going
to call the actor is going to get the state increase d a counter by one and just keep
calling ok so now let me show you what
out the application will look like so there is a very interesting toward that we that is part
of the service property infrastructure that these cody service public explorer and we
explore I can actually see what is running within inside my service
public infrastructure for in this case I have, you know, I have my application
view you see that I have my...lowered application that I deployed before and then I have
this application that is the
counter application and you see that this is basically telling me that these running on
...one so let me show you what the cluster look like
...my local machine I have the service fabric infrastructures basically right now based on
five different nodes so think of like five logical machines
...to get-together and then I have that the application the fabric
application these pacific counter is currently running on...number-one
...bono number one I see that there is the content application I go and
actually I see that disease decode that is actually running on that specific
...so let me make a little bit of
...room here so you see that I have my applications running so let me
do something like I want to simulate to deep
...failure so I have actually let's move these on the debate here
okay so I want to show a failure so what I'm
doing what I'm going to do is here you see that I have no number one I have code and
basically I just say restart and what this means is basically just a processor
...I have a process that...running here and...than just to kill it and we started so
...started and then what I
...see is you see that,
you know, I have my application...stop here?
...to medically might process
we started the actor actually lost the state to but I was
he was able to recover from a fail over and you can think of it over as the node actually failing all the
process failing itself but you see that the windows fabric infrastructure was able to
...to the process and basically get everything upper running and
the client application basically didn't see anything...putting sort of
right the state clearly is different now but, the from the application point of view is like
the actor was always running so let's move back to
d slide deck so what do we what I showed you here is basically
the basic end-to-end developer experience and then also the first very important
...that is the code is reliable so the service fabric
...able...manage the
...over of services when something happens to the
code execution so in this case you see that, you know, the...failed and actually I made
...the service of fabric what...does is potential relocate,
you know, in our case the service the actor service to another node if that specific
nodeis failing or it can we...to the process in such a way that
the guarantee availability so from a client point of view that is nothing or from the application itself
...there is no additional business logic or complex logic that I need to building
to in order to end of that specific...scenario but, you know, as you
saw when the fail over was a pretty what I...I actually lost the state so,
you know, adding you memory only type of state is interesting but for
...case scenario I need to have more than that so let me show you
what imis to take ...stateless a actor in make it statefull
...show...is a very simple to stay process to number-one I define what I
mean by state so I take what I consider to be the adopter that I need to
persist over potentially failures already start and then the only
...need to do is to take that class that I implemented before that
...from an actor and I derived from an actor of t state that basically
...now the actor is actually an actor that...as a stated that I
need to save and replicate what are the actor the reliable actor as
be team and provide out-of-the-box is automatically the management of the
state so for instance I...any change that these made...to the state
...to...is saved a replicated in such a way
that if something goes wrong with my actor I have the ability to restore the state as is and,
then I have...dee ability to a optimize
...control over state like for instance...
is persisted every time that there is a method so when I call a method
the my actor the meta might change state so what...service fabric infrastructure
...is actually to save the state but if I have for instance
our method that I know that is not going to change state what I can use a something that is
...read-only soy mark that specific method as read-only
so that means that is not going to change state so the service fabric infrastructure
can avoid doing the actually state replication and things of that so performance
wise you definitely can benefit from that and in addition to that you can
have as a developer fine-grained control over state and when you want to
...state so we can be quote-unquote on-demand if you need to so let me show you
very quickly what that means so I have let me close
these solution and I want to open another solution that...is the?
So, here I have basically is exactly the same application so the
only difference is I want to show you that is the two things that I need
to do in order to create a statefullservice
...one here you see this class counter state
...the step number one...define what I mean by state
...cases a very simple integer that I want to save it can be, you know,
as complex as you want just need to be a across that these
...elizabeth okay and then here you see that the only difference that I need to make
is I need to specify that now my actor is a
...actor so the ...for actor we...stated that these the
...state that I...and then here the only
difference in the code is my state is
expos quote-unquote with member across member that the state so we
the state I can basically axes the counter state class and from there I
can read and write I can...or get all the method
there so beside that there...nothing ness that...
I need to do so let's go ahead and take these application and deployed again either
...my cluster.
So, I'm going exactly e to the same process I take packaged
application deployed on the cluster and then let me show you first of all
...open the client application
and less that get started.
Okay, so, here I have basically I have a counters is
basicallygoing over is increasing the counters overtime
okay so let me show you one important thing so if I go to the...solutions for
...service explorer let me do refresh?
And, then here now I have the same application because I use exactly the same name
to identify it but let's short here what happens to
...deployment so before you so that...was only one node
active now because I have I asked sort of innocence the
service fabric to take care of the state of the at this point you see that minor might
the probabilities different I have now tree nodes I have one node that these primary where my
...running and then I have to other notes that are course secondary so
...where those node are used in order to replicate the state of
...actor he such a way that if something goes wrong with node number
two with my primary is running I have the ability to recover so
recreated the code restarted the actor...basically you re
...state from one of these two-second ortiz that are running at the same time so
this is basically the typical scenario where you have a state
...clearly the number of replicas where I the state
these replicate can be configure in this case I decide where basically a scenario we tree
...into replicas but I can have one
primary multiple replicas infer really need to...super-high level all
of reliability for my state okay so in this case I have,
you know,the countered is actually running so let me actually sure first of all another
application so if I go back to the same application as before.
So, I have the counter let's run these one...is like before, you know,
that they were showing before that he was just increasing the number but this time let's
do...go through the same process and try to see what happens if I
...these primary so I go to in this case
...number two because now my code these running...
known number two I have code and then basically I...
A actor again so I want to
that you notice one important thing let me stop here you see that
the big difference we respect to the previews example is that what I
see today now is that the countered actually continue and
was not restarted because yes the code wars we started I
kill the process the...but the state...preserved...save...in the
to other secondary that...running along with the primary so as soon as the actor
restarted he was able to recreated this state and
like keywords before the fail over process so this is a very quick
way to show you how you can build actors that can actually also
preserve state across potential...so let's ever quick node.
All statefull actors so do way that
doctors are persisted a something a through what we could providers and there are
...providers in the service fabric so the sort of
...the reliable actors framework comes we
to providers one is volatile state provider this means that
the state is replicated as you see in across multiple
...but is in memory only so in the in that
...if all three nodes goes down
this state is not going to be...saved so this is again
the ee worthwhile for all the case where you need to preserve the state but
...you can afford to lose the state if there is are a drastic
...or of a bb fail over type of scenario order are the
du-rable state provider where along with the keeping the stating memory...is also
...disk and replicate across multiple replicas so these...give you a higher level
...we that clearly a little bit of a performancecost that
these associated with the fact that ...state needs to be persisted on-disk?
This state is manage the state provider is a fully
customizableinterface as you can see her in this slide is a fairly simple
...so potentially if you have are...specific needs where you want to
save stating...specific storage...core document
db or something else you can actually implemented...
your state provider another point you just need to specify that state provider within the actor model
and the after model...that and then you have the ability also to control the
asked...provider either
the assembly level show all the actors belonging to that assembly will use that
specific state provider or you can specify at the act of type so one actor
...by...a...than another actor type.
So, let's ...quick...discussion about scalability so
we discuss a lot about reliability but what about scalability so, you know,
the...one of the key important feature of
high scalable all cloudy type of applications the ability to skate so the way that
...reliable actor scaled is through something that is called
partitions and partition is a way to distribute traffic across
multiple instances of your service so let me try to
I want to show you what that means so let's assume for instance that I have
...this case three different
our clients application they are going to called a
on actor and if I have one partition so basically I'm saying that
I have a way to identify are range okay that basically says
okay how do I want to distribute the traffic across these range and then the default for
...model is basically sixty
to sixty four-bit integer that is used in order to identify sort of the
...additional space for this case let's assume that I define my services with one
...partition so this means...basically no matter what type of
idi create if we go through the single one partitions
...will is our final with one single output innocence and then
these means that basically I have one single actor running in my cluster let's say that, you know,
I want to scale so I want to be able to and-or more traffic so what I can do is
basically to define multiple partition other pointed the undecidable range is
...three different buckets and
other point of depending on the id that I use I might be able to
use the actor belonging to partition number-one partition number two
or partition number trick and then as my traffic increases I can
are the more and more partitions in such a way that I have more
actors or more services that are able to
...my traffic so my traffic is basically spread across multiple instances
so let me show you what that means so if I havethese
...state so the one that we were using before so is already deployed
so one thing that I can do is let me go to?
...state for the client.
And, then I have basically.
I have an application and what I want to show you is
the following actually let me step back before I want to do one more thing so I want to
should the difference between one instances and multiple
one partition and multiple partitions...I have the application that...
was using before let-me open this is the application manifest that is basically what
...application as I was explaining before so as you can see here
I have partition count equal one so this is basically the first case I have
old my traffic going to one single partition let me change that and I want to say that,
you know, right now my traffic is increaase and...I want to be able to
and-or that increased traffic so what they say is now I want to
...we...so they would be sort of time instances of my actor being able to end
on the traffic so let's take the application we deployed so
now I go again go through the deployment process and then?
...go here you see that the
...the old version I have basically these one that is call-you
...one sorry I need to refresh here.
...that the now there is a big difference you
...before I had only one of these entity and these entities are partitions.
Here instead of ten of them now so this means that basically I
have now ten different partitions that are able to...the
traffic so if I have these ten partitions now running so let me see just to make sure
everything is fine yes so if I go to my application and then.
Let's say that I have.
Newm of counters.
...let's say that I want to start with onlyinnocence one.
Okay, so, these case...I used the wrong ...but what basically app
and series that I have one hundred I create one undercut a counters
I deployed of ten...the services deploying
than a partitions so as you can see here basically the traffic that
these coming from the client application...spread across
the depend partitions so you see that each one of them is running
one counter and the traffic from the client is going to go to one of these
partitions and the counter is increased every time...are client
request so as you can see, you know, right now I have a lot of traffic and the traffic is spread across
...ten different partitions so this is a
way to basically I show how...service fabric
...base service fabric application can scale out basically through what
...here that are the partitions okay so let me kill this let's go back to
d slides and thena very quickly kappa just to make sure that, you know,
I...what I covert so, we have these sort of actors that
...sort of these independent...the is somehow helps you to think about
the highly distributed type of system we is so that is not that difficult to
...there is only for basic concepts in order to get started that at the end of they are
not very different from media design patterns like...object-oriented type of application
...state are both reliable so there is no additional code that you need
to writing your application in order to end of those cases fail over and state the
...across...overs and then it is also designed to scale to partitions
...you have the ability basically without and as you get
...you so I didn't change decode of my application I just basically
neat I just needed to change the manifest the application manifest
some sort of meta data redeployment application the point my application was able to
...much better okay is that all...in addition to that for
the reliable actor provide also some additional feature and now we go through some of
them and then probably the last a big question that you might have is but what
how do I upgrade might...potentially without any
interruption and I will I will show you I'll do that?
So,...reliable...the other features available in the app the reliable actors
...very sympathizer said these are very familiar design...soap
authors are just quote-unquote objects so you can take and then pastime around...
is very simple and exception...social propagate so from a developer point of view
...is a very familiar typo programming ...in addition to that
...reliable actors as a...garbage collector like type of process so
these means that the framework is going to check if an actor is going
is it was used
...and if it was not use...actor is mark...
court inactive and then the actual clr dot net the garbage collector attribute
acclaim the memory and this is done in order to optimize memory usage
the ability...so there is location transparency and
...the same time actors are...the fact that the garbage collector collects
...an actor and the actor basically these...it
doesn't have any implication from a client point of view when from the actor proxy I'm going to
...that specific actor if the doctor was collected because it was not
use for a long-time the actor will be recreated the state
...be reiterated completely automatically so again without
any additional business logic that you need to write and then the frequency of dc and
...timeout so hour-long...needs to be active in order
to be collected is something that you can customize in addition to thatsomething that is very
useful for these actor model is the what we call timers and
minors so those are features that allows you toschedule recurring task we
d the...stuff and there is a big the big difference
between timers reminders timers are basically they have the lifespan all-time
it is within the actor lifespan so this means that for
instance the timer is active until the actor is active but if the
...the activated the timer will basicallythe
would be the activate as well so it's not going to fight again instead remind recently that
provide that sort of life-cycle and potentially also failures
so-if my arteries collected or if my actor for any sort of reason failures and
restarted on a different node a reminder is actually going to be active so
...is at the service
fabric level so is something that is persisted over failures and
then there is another feature that we call events that is the ability is a very simple pub
subtype of infrastructure that allows doctors to communicate with the client
application so instead of are typically to add the client to may be do a
sort...type of a scenario where you actually query, you know,
the actors to get the information that you may need you
can register typical delegate and the actors can code that delegate
on the client-side in order to provide forty-some status updates so that
is another feature that provide that these easier to build
...can make easier to build...end-to-end applications a very quick node
she's we're talking about a single threaded but in a multi-threaded type of environment
...up a quick note about concurrency...reliable
...base execution model so doctors are executed intern is
...sort of tadpole like type of mode and then from...
interesting point of view...is basically based on...context
base we intimacy so these means that for instance I have an actor a that is korean actor
be vector b is...actor see the actor see can
...the actor a because...part of the same context right so that is something that
the supported by the platform the same time if for instance you want to
these you might see cases where you want to being able
to detect these sort of...back type of thing the other point you can
...into...point underside pure will be thrown...that sort of scorer
dependencies are happening in while the application is running?
In addition to that because of reliable actors are part of
the service public they have some benefit in addition to that orchestration resource
...is isolation so basically these means that I can also control the placement
on my actors so I can decide where my actors are going to be deployed I can decide that for
instance the actors or the service that is part of my
...infrastructure is going to be...one specific...
my cluster or I might have different type of services we different profiles
...usage o or adopter storage that I can...different
nodes think forty-some of different between I have a machine...my classes that the using
as the versus you know, traditional spinning disks...then.
There is
...support for full operations support...type of scenario when
mice system easing production I have a wide range of different tools as
monitoring cluster manages socio my class thirty perform you see the cluster
explore issue me if the nodes so if they are healthy what is happening my
...so on those are all features that are building a platform
...there is no thing that you need to do in addition in order to be able to add a sort
...productionruntime type of a monitoring
infrastructure there is a lot of emphasis on security so for instance you can
of a fine-grain control over security and, you know,
use different security profiles based on the type of data...so that
...actors or your windows public services are going to end
...soap...all actors that of...dealing with
...data you might want to isolate them...specific node and
...under...low privilege type of account so this is old feature and
...indy service infrastructure.
And, then.
There is the life-cycle so along with the ability to...a...to
have reliable...d service infrastructure provide also the ability to manage the
application life-cycle so for instance and
...want to show youright now is the ability to upgrade
your application without any interruption so less reach back so,
let's kill this if I go to.
Here and then I want todeployed.
And, you application first of all let me show you the code very quickly I
don't want to spend too much time on it by just to give you an idea
...the out the code will look like.
So, this is a services more,
you know, in the for the previews...more user console applications so this is...more
...application where I...a web content type of thing so I have a service here sp
the serving two different versions so I want to show you are you can...grade-a services
using, you know, the...features are there are the interfaces as
...should be from...this point and then there is basically
...one that instead of being a console application is
web from tent so let me show you in...lights very quickly so what
that means basically the architecture of the application so I have a browser
what I want to show is I have a front-end in these cases are project k from
...the project k is all said within the service fabric cluster
...using multiple actors and each actual representup
a moving object that is moving in the browser and I will show you
what that means...that is happening is basically the front-end application is going
to push updates via web circuits to the browser and the browser
...campus is going to update this state and actually the location of all the object
objects and then I want to the from ten does in this case is to query
or the actors in order to get status updates in addition to that the
actors within the actors they're using timers in as a way to
updated that location so what happens is that every thirty milliseconds
of a timer...and then what are the actor does is to update is
a location and then the state of the actor is actually the location itself so basically
the state is persisted so from up...point of view what different dinesh
to do just to collect all the data...to the...a very simple type of from that everything is manager
...the actors in the cluster okay so the application easier I have
just to show you if you are from here this is a typical project k type of application with
...views so on and then the only thing that
dicey here is basically
the way that if I look at this method is from ...
The actor is I basically I'm querying
the actors in order to get...status updates and then we have web sockets I'm going-to
...status updates to the browser so if I go
...what they want to do is
I have the application I already prepackaged application so what I want to do is to
...very simple our...script that using the service fabric publish
I'll comments is going to take the to packages application and
...them ok so what I'm going to do is I said
...deployed so what is
epidemic is I'm connected to my local cluster and what visual studio already
...built-in I'm basically deploying the application in this case I'm deploying
both...version of my application but I'm quote-unquote activating only version
number one okay so you see that here I have basically to applications
version number one and...version number two okay and then the active one is
...out version number one so if I open the browser and
I go to my local machine on board eighty
five or six and you see that I have these sort of very simple let me zooming
...bit so I have basically what we call the visual
...flying objects are moving around you should there is a little bit of a tale the
theater represent basically the state of those actors and those doctors are basically same there
...previous fifty positions and then basically browser is
just rendering the current state of those objects so if I go
to my project...protocol you see that I have a new application
ok the application right now there are q services one is the
state full-service that is the one that is managing over the...actors and then the box one is
basically the project k from the...ok and you see that here I have my
...from chinese running on old one and then era of my actor that are basically spread
across basic time different partitions okay so if I go here and then the
...want to do is you see that I have these flying objects and why do these
guys are running what I want to do is I want to update so this point I have the
seem commoncommon line tool and then what I do is I basically trigger
on update so what is...is basically a styling
...fabric now service fabric now you want to move from version number...
to version number two so let me go here and then if I go to
...service to the service
fabrics product you see that basically what is happening is showing me
...let me do this so we can actually see what is happening real-time?
Is basically telling me that we are going through...process and you
see here that I have different domains upgrade domains and what is happening is
...updating right now a domain update number domain...one and I want tapas
...if we keep looking at this selection remove
this here if we keep looking at this objects you see
...y and the
...service fabric is updating my service some of these object will stop
for a second and those are the objects that are running on that specific
domain upgrade so in the node that belongs to that specific domain...they
stop for a second auc here and then after the domain
upgrade is completed they will
restart the important thing to notice is that state is not lost so from a
...point of view I see that the momentarily they stop and keep in mind that I'm running
a everything on one single machines so clearly here is a little bit
slower than it will happen on scenario but as you can see,
you know, the flying object will stop for a second
they will resume as soon as the...is updated
and the same time you see if you notice that actually the upgrade process
when through because now they are actually rotating so actually upgrade of my
a actors wars adding rotation to the
actor itself ok so here you see that disease in progress I
have three out of five domain upgrades and other point?
The goal here is to show you that you see that these apathy
...downtime upgrade so the
...is still ...with that okay,
so, we so the demo and then
...is basically the end of my presentation there.
There was a lot of material to covert so clearly I will
invite you to take a low-carb artistic a showed the same pose that-you
...in my demo are part of the sdk so you...
locker machine and actually spend more time to look at the code we are going to
poster a more to tortillas same videossoon
...keep a checking these urls and that would be more and more
material and then very important please provide feedback we have
...lot of feature the platform the
run-time service fabric can be used for a while within microsoft that are
...big important services running...the actor...is
relatively new so-if you seen that...basing features or there are
no scenarios that are not easy to implement using the actor with a feature that we having actor
...today please let us know and then we'll will
...best to between,
you know, the tech preview nj to improve as much as we can and
then stay tuned because again as I said, you know, the...is going to be
...a...type of thing so we're going to add more and more scenariosthat are
...will help you to understand the benefit of using
actors for building applications important thing
...I'm not for everything there would be a document that
...the typical design partners and untie partners
four-d actor programming model so that's it I hope that was...for thanks-a-lot?